Guide to the Jewish Communal Registers (Pinkese kehilah) Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional material, 1775-1941; Accession 2008-M-042
  - Notulen boek der pieuse vereeniging, Aṭeret baḥurim gemilut ḥasadim te Borculo, 1896-1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Borculo, The Netherlands. Minute book of the "pious association" of the Jewish community of Borculo, a town in eastern Gelderland, the Netherlands. Includes names of members of the board, records of votes taken, amounts contributed by members, and outlays for communal expenses, such as upkeep of the synagogue, the burial society, and the teacher's salary. The book documents the activities of the Jewish community for almost 50 years and ends mid-sentence in 1941. Manuscript in Dutch with some Hebrew words. [140] p.; 21 cm. Bound with:, Winterswijk: G. Hartog, 1881, 19 p.
  - Pinḳas ha-laz shayakh le-ḥevra ḳadisha de-khan ḳ.ḳ. Palaṭi u-vo nirshamim ha-melaṭshesh. ṿe-gam kol mah she-tserikhim le-ḥ.ḳ. / ṿe-naasah me-ḥadash a-pi ha-gabai Yitsḥaḳ Yosef, 1775-1875 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Varpalota, Hungary. Description provided by vendor: Manuscript on paper. 328 leaves, inlcuding 17 blanks. Written in Ashkenazic cursive script, title page and first few leaves in Ashkenazic square script, title page decorated and framed in blue, red, green and brown gouache, several leaves framed in brown gouache, first 20 leaves paginated in ink in Hebrew letters. Contemporary calf paneled in blind, sunburst pattern on upper cover, edges stained red, lower cover lacking, spine cockled. Although a Jewish minter was mentioned in the annals of Varpalota as early as 1542, significant Jewish settlement in this village some fifty miles west of Budapest did not occur until the beginning of the eighteenth century. The community included a variety of merchants as well as peddlers of local produce. This volume records the membership rolls of Ḥevra ḳadisha members including apprentices over a span of over a century. The scribe, Yitzhak Yosef, creates the chronogram on the title-page by an innovative use of his own name. Manuscript in Hebrew and Yiddish, with the official Hungarian and Hebrew stamp of Chévra ... Egýlet, Várpalotán. [328] l.; 20 cm.
  - Libro de Oro, 1870-1902 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Bucharest, Romania. Register of the Talmud Torah (?) of the Spanish community. Manuscript in Hebrew and Ladino(?). 93 l.; 25 cm.
  - Ḥevrah ḳadisha gemilut ḥasadim; Pinḳas shel ḥevrah ḳadisha gemilut ḥasadim, 643 [1882] (Box 4)
    Hermanshṭadṭ (Sibiu, Romania). Communal register from a social welfare society founded in 632 [1871 or 1872] in the Jewish community of Sibiu, Romania, known in German as Hermannstadt. Luxurious and ornate volume bound in velvet, with engraved silver title plate, latch and trim. Calligraphy and borders in gold, blue, red and black ink. Title page has elaborate micrographic borders made up of biblical verses. Seven pages of by-laws are written in Judeo-German and signed by the leaders of the society in Budapest on October 12, 1882. The rest of the pages are inscribed with names of the members. There is an index in the back of the book for the first 39 names; approximately another hundred names were added subsequently. Manuscript in Yiddish and Hebrew. 42 cm.
  - Zeh ha-pinḳas de-ḥevr. ḳadisha; [Pinḳas ḥevrah ḳadisha], 622 [1861 or 1862] (Box 4)
    Deṿa [Bacia, Romania]. Jewish communal register of a ḥevrah ḳadisha, a term which often refers to a burial society, sometimes with a broader social welfare role as well. The title page includes a calligraphed border with the quotation from responsa on the Mishnah, "Man worries about losing his money; man does not worry about losing his days. His days do not return; his money does not help." The name of the community, Deṿa [Bacia, Romania], appears on p. 31 of the book. The volume contains five pages of by-laws of the society written in Yiddish script and individual pages for each member. The member's names are written in large Hebrew letters, outlined and filled in with stripes, checks, or other decorative patterns, and the vernacular name is written in script at the top of most of the pages. Below each name is a list of the member's pledges and contributions, and if the member died, the date of death. Manuscript in Yiddish and Hebrew. 45 cm.
  - Pinkas of Congregation Beth Abraham, Bayonne City, NJ., 1899-1901 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Account book of the Congregation Beth Abraham, beginning January 8, 1899 and continuing through December 22, 1901. Contains lists of contributions ("Einnahmen"), with the names of contibutors written in Yiddish next to the amounts. Similarly the outlays ("Ausgahben") are listed with the description in Yiddish next to the amount of each expenditure.
  - Pinkas Odobești. Das goldene buch. Carte de aur. Sefer ha-zahav de-bet ha.k.n. Agudat Aḥim 1914 Odobeshṭ, Circa 1904-1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Pinkas (register) of the synagogue Agudat Aḥim, Odobești, Romania. Mainly contains hand-written records of contributions, sometimes in calligraphy or stencilled lettering. Includes names of the men and women who made contributions, names and yahrzeits of the deceased for memorial contributions, and the amount or the item donated. Original leather cover printed in gold ink. Decorative border and the name of the synagogue, Agudat Ahim - בהכ"נ של הפעריין אגודת אחים printed in green and red ink on each page. Manuscript in Hebrew and Romanian.
  - Pinḳas de-Ḥavurah Mishnayot. Pinḳas Iṿeshṭ, 1881 [641] (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Register from the Mishnah study group of the Jewish community of Ivesti, Romania. Contains by-laws of the society, as well as notes and accounts. Manuscript in Hebrew.
  - Zeh ha-pinḳas de-ḥevrah ḳedoshah. Pinḳas de-ḥevrah ḳadisha Iṿeshṭ 688, 1927-1941 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Register from the Ḥevrah Ḳadisha (burial society) of the Jewish community of Ivesti, Romania. Illuminated, gilded title page. The register contains the charter, rules and regulations of the society, its membership roll, associated liturgies, etc. In Hebrew and Yiddish calligraphy, with pages in the back of book written in Romanian. Several pages have colorful borders with floral, architectural, and geometric designs, as well as illumination including eagles, lions, and synagogal elements. On heavy-weight paper.
  - Hoyfṭrekhnung, Pinkas from Serdehaly, Hungary (?), Circa 1865-1867 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Pinkas (register) of a Jewish community, which the vendor identifies as "Serdehaly, Hungary, 1867." List of the members and their contibutions for seats in the synagogue, as well as "mitsvos geld," or contributions in honor of occasions throughout the year. Also includes lists of expenses and recipients of charitable support. Title page includes the saying: Zore'a tsedaḳah śekher emet ("he that sows righteousness has a sure reward," Prov. 11:18). Manuscript in Hebrew and Yiddish.
- Additional material, 1756?-1945; Accession 2015-M-005
  - Belarus
    - Taḳanot Anṭopol, Circa 1800-1900 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Book of takanot (by-laws) of the Oraḥ Ḥayim Society from the Jewish community of Antopalʹ. The members of the society met daily for Torah study and also raised money for the poor. The last page of the book is signed by the scribe Shemuʼel Pisatsḳi of Anṭipolye. The rabbi of Antipolye during this period was Pinḥas Mikhaʼel Roḳeaḥ. In Hebrew. [10] pages; 23 centimeters.
  - Germany
    - Izraelitish religiozer ferayn di Edesheyst, 1830-1877 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Register from the Israelite Religious Union, Heidesheim, Germany. At the top of the title page is the Hebrew saying, "Every gathering that is for the sake of Heaven, will endure" (Avot 4:14). According to the vendor, this pinkas is quite rare because of its place of origin. It starts with twenty takanot (by-laws) signed by the board, continuing with information about the community, meetings, decisions, and so forth. Mainly in Yiddish, with some Hebrew and German. 80 leaves (1-28 have writing on both sides, 29-31 have been removed, and the rest are blank); 22 centimeters.
  - Hungary
    - Pinḳas Ḥevrah Ḳadisha de-Ḳ.Ḳ. Győr, 1928-1937 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Register book of the Jewish burial society (Ḥevrah Ḳadisha) of Győr, Hungary. The pages of the book are printed mainly in Hungarian, with Hebrew and Hungarian headings at the top of each page. Over 400 of the pages are filled in with handwritten particulars in Hebrew and Hungarian about each member of the community who died. Information includes Hebrew and Hungarian names, dates of death and burial, age, names of parents, contributions and expenses. 240 [that is, 480] pages; 36 centimeters.
    - Zeh ha-pinḳas shayakh le-ḥevra ḳadisha de-gemilut ḥasadim de-yishuv Holash, Circa 1826-1875 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Register of a Jewish welfare society in the town of Kiskunhalas (Halas, Olaš), Hungary. The title page is calligraphed and decorated in color. The first few pages have signatures of the board and the by-laws of the society. The rest of the volume contains pages with details about the accounts of each of the members. The title page is dated 587 [1826 or 1827], while entries seem to be dated later in the nineteenth century, at least as late as the 1870's. At the end of the volume there is a description of the cemetery. In Yiddish and Hebrew. 1 volume; 36 centimeters.
  - Israel
    - Pinḳas yeshivat Ziḳne talmide ḥakhamim ha-kelalit, Circa 1910-1914 (Box 3)
      The Central Jew's Age Shelter (Yeshivat Zikne Talmide Hakhamim ha-Kelalit) was founded in Jerusalem in 1907 to help elderly Torah scholars from the Diaspora live their last days in Jerusalem. This pinkas, or register, from the yeshiva contains by-laws of the institution, including policies with regard to medical attention for the scholars; "Shadar" letters dated 1910-1914 empowering various emissaries to collect contributions in America for this institute; and lists of donors. The letters are signed by the administration and members of the Jerusalem rabbinical court as well as visiting rabbis, including autograph signatures and stamps of famous rabbis such as Joseph Chaim Sonenfeld, David Tipman, Joseph Yehuda Strassburg, Nachum Ber Fraiman and others. The lists of contributors include amounts, names and the communities of the donors: Boston, Roxbury, Dorchester, Malden, Maplewood, Chelsea, Cambridge, Brookline, New London, Hartford, Norwich, Plymouth, Rhode Island, and more. Manuscript in Hebrew, various hands, calligraphic colored title page. [43] leaves; 30 centimeters. New binding.
  - Latvia
    - Zeh ha-pinḳas shayakh le-vet ha-midrash yashan ḳ.ḳ. Lutsin, 1805-1858 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Register book from the Jewish community of Ludza, Latvia. The register contains records of the old House of Study, including financial accounts, decisions, and minutes of meetings signed by members of the board. Manuscript in Hebrew. 115 [that is, 230] pages; 34 centimeters.
    - Pinḳas shel ḥevra shulḥan ʻarukh, Lutsin, 1837-1923 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Register book from a study group in Ludza, Latvia focusing on the major code of Jewish law, the Shulḥan ʻArukh. The Jewish community of Ludza dates back to the 17th century and grew to over 1,500 Jews by the early 20th century, establishing at least eight synagogues and houses of study. The register, which spans almost a century, includes by-laws and other records of the study group signed by rabbis and members of the society. The title page has a pen-and-ink decorated border and an official stamp in Hebrew, "Belongs to the Shulhan Arukh Society of the holy congregation of Lutsin." Manuscript in Hebrew. The date is written on title page in the chronogram, Oraḥ ḥayim le-maʻalah le-maśkil. 90 [that is, 180] pages; 22 centimeters.
  - Lithuania
    - Pinḳas Skuodas, 1912-1918 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Register from the Jewish community of Skuodas, Lithuania. The first section of the notebook contains records of meetings and decisions of leaders of the community, with the signatures of the committee members. The rest of the manuscript contains biblical exegesis, mainly but not exclusively on the books of Judges and Samuel. Manuscript in Hebrew. Approximately [130] pages (some blank); 22 centimeters. Repaired and rebound using original covers.
  - Netherlands
    - [Collection of constitutions and regulations of Jewish organizations in the Netherlands], Circa 1800-1900 (Box 5, Folder 1-50)
      Collection of fifty small printed books containing by-laws of Jewish organizations in the Netherlands, mainly synagogues and local branches of the Nederlands-Israëlitisch Kerkgenootschap. Some of the books contain handwritten signatures or annotations by an officer of the organization. In Dutch. 50 volumes; 14-24 centimeters.
  - Poland
    - Pinḳas Zgierz, 1915-1930 (Box 6)
      Manuscript register from the Jewish community council of Zgierz, Poland containing protocols covering the fifteen-year period from 1915 to 1930. Zgierz, a city in the Lodz province of central Poland, had a Jewish population of approximately 4,000 during these years. The order of the protocols is not continuous: at the front of the volume are protocols no. 406-413 (1930), followed by no. 1-13 (1915-1917), one unnumbered protocol from 1918, and then the rest of the protocols, no.1-405. A detailed description by Y. A Malchieli of this manuscript has been published in the Book of Zgierz (Hebrew, 1975; English translation, 2007) and on the JewishGen website. Malchieli writes that the Communal Council dealt with "matters of ritual slaughter (shechita), schools, prayers, bathhouses, cemeteries, the various assistance and support organizations serving the needy, religious affairs and other matters. As well, it served as the official representative body of the Jewish community to the various governments and other causes. The Communal Council oversaw a staff of workers and a variety of institutions and funds. To support its activities, it imposed taxes upon the community..." The protocols in this volume record discussions about all of these matters as well as important events affecting the community including pogroms, anti-semitism, Zionism and Jewish settlements in the land of Israel. In Hebrew, Yiddish, Polish and German. [276] pages; 37 centimeters.
  - Romania
    - Sefer ha-taḳanot shel ha-ḥevrah gemilut ḥasadim she-nityasdah bi-shenat 632 poh ʻir Baḳoy, 1874 or 1875 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Register of a communal welfare society n Bacau, Romania. The impressive title page has colorful calligraphy and illumination with columns, mythical creatures and official stamps of the community. The date on the title page is 5535 [1874 or 1875]. The register was written by the sexton Yaakov Shemuel Segal, the treasurer of the society, Shimon Rekht, and the secretary of the society, Hayim Ozer Kroiz. The volume contains by-laws of the society written in Yiddish followed by lists of yahrtzeits. The lists include names of men and women for each month of the year beginning with Nisan. [36] pages (11 blank); 31 centimeters. Original tooled leather binding, worn condition.
    - Dizer bukh ... (Birlad, Romania), 1905 or 1906 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      This bound cloth book is an artifact from the Jewish community of Bîrlad, located in the central Moldavian region of Romania. At the beginning of the twentieth century Bîrlad had a Jewish population of over 5,000, with numerous synagogues and houses of prayer among other institutions. In this volume the text is printed on fabric which has been sewn together with pockets to hold cards for the congregants receiving honors at the High Holiday services. The cards are numbered, possibly with the seat numbers of the donors. In Yiddish. [36] pages; 34 centimeters.
    - …Zeh ha-pinḳas shayakh le-ḥavurah sandlars, 1832-1909 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Register from the society of shoemakers in Botoșani, Romania. Includes by-laws, lists of members, pages with names of women in the back, and other notations. Date on the cover is 593 [1832 or 1833]; pages are dated as late as 669 [1908 or 1909]. In Yiddish. Approximately 100 leaves (about half are blank); 35 centimeters. Original tooled leather binding with gold colored patterns on front and spine.
    - Pinkas me-Bukarest; Zeh ha-pinḳas shayakh le-vet ha-keneset yashan ha-nikra bet ha-midrash mi-Bokoresht, 1846-1873 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Register from a synagogue and house of study in Bucharest, Romania. The introduction describes the turbulent history of the community: the holy society ("havurah kedoshah") was established in 1794, but when hard times forced Jews to flee the city the first register book was lost. The second pinkas, written in 1800, was also destroyed when a fire burned thousands of houses along with the old synagogue. Years later a member of the society recovered the original pinkas, and this volume, which is dated 607 [1846 or 1847], contains a copy of the thirteen original by-laws. There are several philosophical texts--treatises on cosmogony and theology, as well as lists of members of the society. Some of the entries are dated as late as 633 [1872 or 1873]. The entire text, except for one page in script in the back of the volume, is written in neat, legible calligraphy, the introduction in Rashi script and the rest in block letters. In Hebrew. Approximately 75 leaves (mostly blank; approximately 20 pages with text); 40 centimeters. Original leather cover with title and ornamentation stamped in gold ink.
    - Pinkas de-havurta kadishta de-poh k.k. Krayove, 1846-1907 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Register of the Hevrah Kadisha (burial society) of the Jewish community of Craiova, Romania. The register contains by-laws and decisions signed by leaders and members of the society, as well as accounts of various events in the community, such as a dispute between a group of more modern Jewish people who wanted to transport the deceased to the cemetery in a new wagon, while members of the Hevrah Kadisha insisted on carrying the body according to the old custom on a stretcher by foot. The volume has two illuminated title pages. The first, dated 607 [that is, 1846 or 1847] is in colored ink and paint. At the top of the page a lion is depicted crouched within the arched frieze of a portal. On either side are two columns, supported beneath by a panel with marble-like decoration. The title is written in calligraphy in the middle of the page surrounded by fine geometric patterns which have been drawn or printed and applied to the page. The second title page is illuminated in black ink, with intricate lettering in different styles inside geometric and floral borders. This page is dated 5608 [1847 or 1848]. It is signed by Solomon Löbel. A page with a colorful painted border chronicles events in the community's history including the pogroms and expulsion of many of the Jews in 1885, signed by David Yosef ben Mosheh Yehuda Psalter Shats, the cantor of the synagogue, dated Kislev and Tishre 5668 [1907]. The register is written in Yiddish and in Hebrew. 44 pages; 42 centimeters.
    - …Pinḳas meha-Ḥavurah Mishnayot ṿe-Shas, 1877 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      Register from a society for Mishnah and Talmud study, including an introduction and twenty-two by-laws. Calligraphy in block letters and Rashi script with decorative elements. The colophon on page 11b is dated 28 Tamuz 5637 [1877], Krasnye. The town of Crasna (Kraszna in Hungarian) is in the region of Transylvania--Hungary at the time this volume was written, but now part of Romania. In Hebrew. 13 [that is, 26] pages; 22 centimeters. New binding.
    - Procese verbale / Epitropia Comunitatei Israelite Dorohoi, 1909/1910, 1929-1931 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
      Two bound volumes containing records of meetings of the Jewish community council of Dorohoi, Romania. The books apparently come from a larger set. The records include the dates of the meetings, lists of members present or absent, and the minutes of the meetings signed by the attendees. Written in Romanian. These two volumes are numbered: Inventar Archiva No.37. 1909/1910 -- Inventar Archiva No. 43. 1929/1930/1931. 2 volumes (approximately 200 and 500 pages); 34 centimeters.
    - …Pinḳas Ṭempel Bet Yaʻaḳov de Nayshaṭts Yassi, Circa 1910-circa 1930 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      This volume appears to be the register of a burial society in Iași, Romania. It contains memorial prayers and the names of members and their families. The register is from the early twentieth century, but some notatons were added later. Mainly in Hebrew with some Yiddish. In the back of the register there is a letter dated 9/XII/1943 offering congratulations on the birth of a granddaughter and expressing hope for better times. Approximately 50 pages; 32 centimeters.
    - Statuele comunitatii autonome ortodoxe evreesti din Medias, 1939 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      By-laws of the Orthodox Jewish community of Medias, Romania. Mimeographed copy on onion-skin paper. In Romanian. 23 leaves; 29 centimeters.
    - Pinḳas shel ha-ḥevrah ḳedoshah Pyaṭra; Pinkas Societate "Sacra" din Piatra, 1770-1934 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Register of the Hevrah Kadisha [burial or communal welfare society] of Piatra Neamt, Romania. Includes by-laws of the society, lists of members, information about the local Jewish community and cemetery, and accounts of historical events and interesting happenings. Manuscript in Hebrew and Romanian. Many of the pages are illuminated in color. Original leather binding and box engraved with a six-pointed star and the inscription "Pinkas from the Hevrah Kadisha from the year 5531, here in Piatra." On the title page of the register the year 5531 [1770 or 1771] is crossed out and 5461 [1700 or 1701] written beneath. Entries were added to the volume until 1934. 84 leaves (some pages are blank or missing); 30 centimeters.
    - Pinḳas Ṿaslui, 1880-1945 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      Register of the synagogue on Hosh Street in Vaslui, Romania. The volume includes a chronology of important dates from the year the synagogue was founded in 1873, customs of the synagogue, duties of its officers, and the names of donors and those being memorialized. The entries are from various dates, with the last writings from 1944-1945 describing the Holocaust and mentioning the death of U.S. President Franklin Roosevelt. The description of the Holocaust is written in the style of the Scroll of Esther. Most of the pages are blank; there are seventeen pages with writing. The title page has a decorative border and lettering. The introduction, signed by David Pakhter, and title page are both dated the third day of Hol ha-Moed Sukkot 5641 [1880]. In Hebrew and Yiddish. 100 pages (83 blank); 38 centimeters. Re-bound in new leather binding.
  - Russia
    - Pinḳas ḥevrah biḳur ḥolim ṿe-hakhnasat kalah, 1888-1928 (Box 11)